Guide to the Cornell University examinations, 1869-1931.
Cornell University examinations,
- Series I. Examination Questions - Assorted
  - Cornell University - Freshman Latin - Nepos, 1889-12-20 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    One section labeled (I); 12 numbered questions on first page under "Translation at Hearing, Etc., and Writing From Memory"; passage is from Ages. 2, I-2; question 1: "What mode and what tense do you expect?"
  - Cornell University - Freshman Latin - Cicero: De Senectute, 1890-03-19 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    2 sections (I, II); section I has one passage followed by 6 questions; section II has writing and translation passages (6 numbered questions)
  - Cornell University - Freshman Latin - Livy., 1890-06-02 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    2 sections (I, II); section I has one passage followed by 7 questions; section II has writing and translation passages (4 numbered questions)
  - Sophomore Latin - Terence: History of Roman Literature, Fall Term, 1890-12-17 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    First set of questions (1-4) on translation and a passage; second set of questions (1-5) on Roman literature; second question 1: "Describe, briefly, the Roman theatre in the time of Terence."
  - Sophomore Latin - Horace - Odes and Epistles - Spring Term, 1891-06-06 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    2 sections (I, II); questions 1-5 under section I; questions 1-4 under section II; question I.1 begins: "Translate (at sight) Epist. I, 19, 1-14"
  - Sophomore Latin - Horace: Epodes, Satires, and (in part) Odes - Winter Term, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    2 sections (I, II); questions 1-5 under section I; questions 1-5 under section II; section II on History of Roman Literature; question II.1 begins: "Give, approximately, the dates of publication of …"
  - Cornell University - Greek A, 1890-03-20 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    4 questions (1-4) on translation; question 4 begins: "Translate into Greek: …" and has 5 numbered sentences for translating
  - Grecian History, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    10 questions; question 1: "Discuss the geography of Greece in its larger sense"
  - Greek History, 1889-12-18 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Annotated; 10 questions; question 1 begins: "Give Curtius' theory of the settlement of Greece"
  - Grecian and Roman History and Ancient Geography, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Lightly annotated; 3 sections (I-III); question III.2: "Where was Euboea, --Mt. Olympus, --the Maeander?"
  - Roman History, 1890-03-17 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Annotated; 10 questions; question 10 has parts a-j; question 1: "Enumerate the sources from which the early Roman annalists obtained their information"
  - Roman History (133 B.C. - 476 A.D.), 1890-06-09 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Annotated; 9 questions; question 9: "The state of Christianity in the time of Constantine."
  - Cornell University - French Department, Freshman Year, First Term, 1889-12-18 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    3 sections (I-III); sections II and III are on translation; question I.1 begins: "Conjugate in full the following tenses …"
  - Cornell University - Literary Courses - Department of Romance Language, First Year, Second Term, 1890-03-17 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Exam in French; 5 sections (I-V); 30 numbered questions under section IV; question V.1: "State the formation, comparison and position of adjectives"
  - Cornell University - Literary French - Department of Romance Languages, Course I, 1890-06-09 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    5 sections (I-V); all sections are on translation; 20 sentences to be translated under section IV; 26 sentences to translate to English under section V
  - Cornell University - Department of Romance Languages, French, Course 2, 1890-06-09 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    4 sections (I-IV); sections I, II, III on translation, at sight; 3 questions under section IV; question IV.2: "Mention the most important results of the Romantic mvoement."
  - Cornell University - Department of Romance Languages, Course 2, 1890-12-19 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Exam in French; 4 sections (I-IV); sections I, II, IV on translation; 4 questions under section III; question III.1: "Give a brief sketch of Corneille's life."
  - Cornell University - Department of Romance Languages, Course 2, 1891-03-23 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Exam in French; 4 sections (I-IV); sections I, II, III on translation; section IV begins: "Give a brief biographical sketch of any two of the following writers of the Romantic School: …"
  - Cornell University - Department of Romance Languages, Course 2, 1891-06-09 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Exam in French; 2 sections (I, II); passage in section I is from Sainte Beuve, Causeries du Lundi and passage in section II is from Mrime, Tamango; section II has 5 questions; question II.1: "What do you understand by Romanticiism?"
  - Cornell University - Department of Romance Languages, Course 6, 1891-12-22 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Exam in French; 3 sections (I-III) on translation; section III is "Translation at Hearing"
  - Cornell University - German Department, First year, First Term, 1889-12-19 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    3 sections (I-III); section II begins: "Write the nominative and genitive singular, and the nominative plural with the appropriate form of …"
  - Cornell University - German Department, First year, Second Term, 1890-03-18 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    4 sections (I-IV); section II begins: "Give the principal parts of the following verbs: …"
  - Cornell University - German Department, First year, Third Term, 1890-06-10 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    3 sections (I-III); section II begins: "Explain the syntax of …"
  - Maria Stuart, 1890-12 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Exam in German; 4 sections (I-IV); section IV: "Give a brief sketch of Mary's life. In what respects does the play depart from historic accuracy?"
  - Lessing's Prose, 1891-03 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Exam in German; lightly annotated; 2 sections (I-II); section II: "Give a brief sketch of Lessing's life and literary activity."
  - Sophomore German, 1891-06 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    2 sections (I, II); section I on "Lessing's Prose" and section II on "Hermann and Dorothea"
  - Department of German, Cornell University - Gtz, and Goethe's Prose, 1892-03 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    2 sections (I, II); section I has parts (a.)-(e.); section II has 3 questions; question II.1: "What were the main features of Goethe's residence in Strasburg?"
  - Department of German, Cornell University, 1892-06 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    No original title; 2 sections (I, II); section I on "Egmont" and has 6 passages to translate; section II has 3 questions; question II.3: "Discuss Schiller's criticisms of the play."
  - Physics - 2a: Examination in Mechanics, 1891-12-16 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Handwritten exam; annotated at the bottom; 3 P.M. - 5:30 P.M.; 6 questions; question 1 begins: "State and explain Newton's Laws of Motion"
  - Course 2a Physics - Electricity and Magnetism, Spring Term, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Handwritten exam; annotated at the bottom; 6 questions; question 1 begins: "Describe the tangent galvanometer."
  - Preliminary Examination - Logic, 1890-11-25 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Annotated; 5 questions; question 1: "Explain Intension and Extension of Words."
  - Logic, 1890-12-16 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Annotated; 8-10 A.M.; 8 questions; question 1 has parts a-c and begins: "Give the Contradictory, the Contrary, the Subalternate or Subalternant of: …"
  - Logic and Psychology, 1891-03-20 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Annotated; 8-10 A.M.; 2 sections (I, II); questions 1-2 under section I and questions 1-5 under section II; question II.1 begins: "Give a definition of Physiological Psychology."
  - Examination in Physiological Psychology, 1891-06-05 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Handwritten exam; annotated; 8 questions; question 3 begins: "What is imagination?"
  - Sophomore Rhetoric, 1890-12-17 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    5 topics (I-V); Topics: I. The Paragraph, II. Invention, III. Invention, IV. The Plan, V. The Development
  - Sophomore Rhetoric, 1891-03-21 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    5 questions (I-V); question I.1 begins: "What is meant by interpretation?"
  - Sophomore Rhetoric, 1891-06-06 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    5 questions; question 1: "What is the difference between Testimony and Authority? Illustrate."
  - Oratory, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Handwritten exam; 24 questions; question 1: "In what 3 ways does an oration differ from an essay?"
  - The Institutes of Education, 1892-12-19 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    9 questions; question 1 begins: "Give a general statement of the scope of education as a science … "
  - The Institutes of Education, 1893-03-18 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    10 questions; question 1 begins: "Show by a linear diagram the order in which the members of the …"
  - Cornell University - School of Law - Examination in Elementary Law and Contracts - Juniors, Fall Term, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    17 questions; question 1 begins: "What is the common law?"
  - Cornell University - School of Law - Examination in Contracts - Juniors, Winter Term, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    16 questions; question 1 begins: "Explain the following words as used in the seventeenth section of the Statute of Frauds …"
  - Examination Notes in Military Science and Tactics, 1892-03 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    3 sections: Military Science, Art of War, Military Law
  - Questions on the Lectures and on the Text, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Handwritten exam; subject unknown/could not be deciphered; questions 1-4 on the Lectures; questions 5-12 on the Text
- Series II. Examination Schedules and Rules of Conduct
  - Assorted Exams and Non-Exams (1 of 3), 1870-1884, 1917, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Cornell University - The Graduate School - Schedule of Examinations, Advanced Degrees, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes an alphabetical list of names and their exams and a list of exams arranged by dates
  - Cornell University - College of Arts and Sciences for Conduct of Examinations and Cases of Fraud in More than One College, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Assorted Exams and Non-Exams (3 of 3), 1871-1873, undated, ca. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cornell University - Office of the Registrar - Explanation of Grading Systems, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cornell University - List of Candidates and Schedule of Examinations for Advanced Degrees, 1892-1913 (Box 1, Volume 4)
    No 1894, 1906, 1908-1912; note card from H.S. White, Chairman of the Committee on Graduate Work to Dean's Office, University Faculty
  - Botany - Arrangement of Lectures and Examinations in the General Course - Spring Term, 1879 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - The Cornell University - Programme of Examinations, 1878; Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; booklet of schedules of exams; "Entrance Examinations" and "Term Examinations" (Box 1, Volume 2)
- Series III. Entrance Examinations
  - Cornell University - Entrance Examinations - Grammar, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Slightly annotated; 21 questions; question 21 has 22 options; question 1: "Which letters of the English Alphabet are mutes?"
  - The Cornell University - Entrance Examination in Geography, 1875-09-14 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    9 questions; question 1 begins: "Draw an outline map of the United States as large as your paper will allow; …"
  - Cornell University, Entrance Examinations - Arithmetic, 1880-19-14 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 8 questions; question 1 begins: "Define a prime number, …"
  - Cornell University, Entrance Examinations - Arithmetic, 1881-01-04 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 8 questions; question 1 begins: "Define: a unit, a compound fraction, a complex fraction, …"
  - Cornell University - Entrance Examinations: Grammar, 1871 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Cornell University - Entrance Examination in Grammar, 1874-06-30; Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 14 questions; exam is in red ink; question 1 begins: "What are the labials? …" (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Cornell University - Partial Entrance Examination in Latin, 1877-06-19; Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 3 parts (I - III) (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Cornell University - Partial Entrance Examination in Latin, 1878-06-19; Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 5 parts (I - V) (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - German Entrance Examinations, 1877-06-20; Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 3 parts (I - III) (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Solid Geometry - Entrance Examination, 1879-06-18; Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 8 a.m.; 6 questions; question 1 begins: "Define: two parallel planes, …" (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Trigonometry - Entrance Examination, 1879-06-18; Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten exam; 10 (1/2) a.m.; 8 questions; question 1 begins: "Define tangent of an angle, …" (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Higher Algebra, Entrance Examination, 1879-06-18; Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten exam; Room II; 10 questions; question 3 begins: "Prove that, the number of permutations of n things …" (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Plane Geometry - Entrance Examination, 1879-06-16; Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 9 a.m.; 6 questions; question 1 begins: "Define: a postulate, a straight line, a square, …" (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Entrance Exams - English, 1897-06-1931-09; Includes an old envelop addressed to the College Entrance Exmaination Board; exams of years 1897-1920 were in this envelope (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Samples of Entrance and Scholarship Examination Papers, 1910-1912 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Cornell University - Examination Papers - Miscellaneous, 1889-1893, undated; All papers initialed "K.J. 1893" at the bottom (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Entrance Examination in Latin, 1889-09; 7 questions on translation and passages; question 1 begins: "Translate (at sight) Cic. Brutus, I, 1" (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cornell University - Examination in Entrance Greek, 1890-09-29; 10 questions (I - X); question II begins: "Questions on the preceding passage: (1) Difference between the force of …" (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cornell University - Question Papers Used at the Examinations for Admission and at the Examinations for University Scholarships, 1890-1901 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - Cornell University - Question Papers Given at the Examinations for Admission and at the Examinations for University Scholarships, 1902-1909; No 1907, 1908 (Box 2, Volume 6)
- Series IV. Other
  - Cornell University - Examination Papers - Miscellaneous, 1889-1893, undated; All papers initialed "K.J. 1893" at the bottom (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cornell University - Department of Military Science and Tactics - Memorandum No. 3, H.E. Tutherly, Professor, 1892-03-09 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letter of Transmission of Examination Papers from Mr. Kirby Jones, 1930-11-26; A piece of correspondence between Executive Secretary Harold Flack to Professor Otto Kinkeldey; copies of letters from Mr. Kirby Jones (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Charles David Damsky - Mechanical Engineering - Old Prelims, 1913-1917, undated; From Courses E 14, E 15, and E 35; includes data sheets from Lefax Filing Index: Operation of Mechanical Stokers, Rated Tractive Force of Locomotives, Superheated Ammonia Vapor; includes annotated Jacksonian Democracy -"Readings for History 53 collateral to Fish, Ch. X-XV" (Box 2, Folder 9)